so you can actually have on the order of a 250-mile range. CA: I mean, those battery packs are incredibly heavy, but you think the math can still work out intelligently -- by combining light body, heavy battery, you can still gain spectacular efficiency. EM: Exactly. The rest of the car has to be very light to offset the mass of the pack, and then you have to have a low drag coefficient so that you have good highway range. And in fact, customers of the Model S are sort of competing with each other to try to get the highest possible range. I think somebody recently got 420 miles out of a single charge. CA: Bruno Bowden, who's here, did that, broke the world record.EM: Congratulations. CA: That was the good news. The bad news was that to do it, he had to drive at 18 miles an hour constant speed and got pulled over by the cops. (Laughter) EM: I mean, you can certainly drive -- if you drive it 65 miles an hour, under normal conditions, 250 miles is a reasonable number. CA: Let's show that second video showing the Tesla in action on ice. Not at all a dig at The New York Times, this, by the way. What is the most surprising thing about the experience of driving the car? EM: In creating an electric car, the responsiveness of the car is really incredible. So we wanted really to have people feel as though they've almost got to mind meld with the car, so you just feel like you and the car are kind of one, and as you corner and accelerate, it just happens, like the car has ESP. You can do that with an electric car because of its responsiveness. You can't do that with a gasoline car. I think that's really a profound difference, and people only experience that when they have a test drive. CA: I mean, this is a beautiful but expensive car. Is there a road map where this becomes a mass-market vehicle? EM: Yeah. The goal of Tesla has always been to have a sort of three-step process, where version one was an expensive car at low volume, version two is medium priced and medium volume, and then version three would be low price, high volume. So we're at step two at this point. So we had a $100,000 sports car, which was the Roadster. Then we've got the Model S, which starts at around 50,000 dollars. And our third generation car, which should hopefully be out in about three or four years will be a $30,000 car. But whenever you've got really new technology, it generally takes about three major versions in order to make it a compelling mass-market product. And so I think we're making progress in that direction, and I feel confident that we'll get there. CA: I mean, right now, if you've got a short commute, you can drive, you can get back, you can charge it at home. There isn't a huge nationwide network of charging stations now that are fast. Do you see that coming, really, truly, or just on a few key routes? EM: There actually are far more charging stations than people realize, and at Tesla we developed something called a Supercharging technology, and we're offering that if you buy a Model S for free, forever. And so this is something that maybe a lot of people don't realize. We actually have California and Nevada covered, and we've got the Eastern seaboard from Boston to D.C. covered. By the end of this year, you'll be able to drive from L.A. to New York just using the Supercharger network, which charges at five times the rate of anything else. And the key thing is to have a ratio of drive to stop, to stop time, of about six or seven. So if you drive for three hours, you want to stop for 20 or 30 minutes, because that's normally what people will stop for. So if you start a trip at 9 a.m., by noon you want to stop to have a bite to eat, hit the restroom, coffee, and keep going. CA: So your proposition to consumers is, for the full charge, it could take an hour. So it's common -- don't expect to be out of here in 10 minutes. Wait for an hour, but the good news is, you're helping save the planet, and by the way, the electricity is free. You don't pay anything. EM: Actually, what we're expecting is for people to stop for about 20 to 30 minutes, not for an hour. It's actually better to drive for about maybe 160, 170 miles and then stop for half an hour and then keep going. That's the natural cadence of a trip. CA: All right. So this is only one string to your energy bow. You've been working on this solar company SolarCity. What's unusual about that? EM: Well, as I mentioned earlier, we have to have sustainable electricity production as well as consumption, so I'm quite confident that the primary means of power generation will be solar. I mean, it's really indirect fusion, is what it is. We've got this giant fusion generator in the sky called the sun, and we just need to tap a little bit of that energy for purposes of human civilization. What most people know but don't realize they know is that the world is almost entirely solar-powered already. If the sun wasn't there, we'd be a frozen ice ball at three degrees Kelvin, and the sun powers the entire system of precipitation. The whole ecosystem is solar-powered. CA: But in a gallon of gasoline, you have, effectively, thousands of years of sun power compressed into a small space, so it's hard to make the numbers work right now on solar, and to remotely compete with, for example, natural gas, fracked natural gas. How are you going to build a business here? EM: Well actually, I'm confident that solar will beat everything, hands down, including natural gas. (Applause)CA: How? EM: It must, actually. If it doesn't, we're in deep trouble. CA: But you're not selling solar panels to consumers. What are you doing? EM: No, we actually are. You can buy a solar system or you can lease a solar system. Most people choose to lease. And the thing about solar power is that it doesn't have any feed stock or operational costs, so once it's installed, it's just there. It works for decades. It'll work for probably a century. So therefore, the key thing to do is to get the cost of that initial installation low, and then get the cost of the financing low, because that interest -- those are the two factors that drive the cost of solar. And we've made huge progress in that direction, and that's why I'm confident we'll actually beat natural gas. CA: So your current proposition to consumers is, don't pay so much up front. EM: Zero.CA: Pay zero up front. We will install panels on your roof. You will then pay, how long is a typical lease? EM: Typical leases are 20 years, but the value proposition is, as you're sort of alluding to, quite straightforward. It's no money down, and your utility bill decreases. Pretty good deal. CA: So that seems like a win for the consumer. No risk, you'll pay less than you're paying now. For you, the dream here then is that -- I mean, who owns the electricity from those panels for the longer term? I mean, how do you, the company, benefit? EM: Well, essentially, SolarCity raises a chunk of capital from say, a company or a bank. Google is one of our big partners here. And they have an expected return on that capital. With that capital, SolarCity purchases and installs the panel on the roof and then charges the homeowner or business owner a monthly lease payment, which is less than the utility bill. CA: But you yourself get a long-term commercial benefit from that power. You're kind of building a new type of distributed utility. EM: Exactly. What it amounts to is a giant distributed utility. I think it's a good thing, because utilities have been this monopoly, and people haven't had any choice. So effectively it's the first time there's been competition for this monopoly, because the utilities have been the only ones that owned those power distribution lines, but now it's on your roof. So I think it's actually very empowering for homeowners and businesses. CA: And you really picture a future where a majority of power in America, within a decade or two, or within your lifetime, it goes solar? EM: I'm extremely confident that solar will be at least a plurality of power, and most likely a majority, and I predict it will be a plurality in less than 20 years. I made that bet with someone —CA: Definition of plurality is? EM: More from solar than any other source. CA: Ah. Who did you make the bet with? EM: With a friend who will remain nameless. CA: Just between us. (Laughter) EM: I made that bet, I think, two or three years ago, so in roughly 18 years, I think we'll see more power from solar than any other source. CA: All right, so let's go back to another bet that you made with yourself, I guess, a kind of crazy bet. You'd made some money from the sale of PayPal. You decided to build a space company. Why on Earth would someone do that? (Laughter) EM: I got that question a lot, that's true. People would say, "Did you hear the joke about the guy who made a small fortune in the space industry?" Obviously, "He started with a large one," is the punchline. And so I tell people, well, I was trying to figure out the fastest way to turn a large fortune into a small one. And they'd look at me, like, "Is he serious?" CA: And strangely, you were. So what happened? EM: It was a close call. Things almost didn't work out. We came very close to failure, but we managed to get through that point in 2008. The goal of SpaceX is to try to advance rocket technology, and in particular to try to crack a problem that I think is vital for humanity to become a space-faring civilization, which is to have a rapidly and fully reusable rocket. CA: Would humanity become a space-faring civilization? So that was a dream of yours, in a way, from a young age? You've dreamed of Mars and beyond? EM: I did build rockets when I was a kid, but I didn't think I'd be involved in this. It was really more from the standpoint of what are the things that need to happen in order for the future to be an exciting and inspiring one? And I really think there's a fundamental difference, if you sort of look into the future, between a humanity that is a space-faring civilization, that's out there exploring the stars, on multiple planets, and I think that's really exciting, compared with one where we are forever confined to Earth until some eventual extinction event. CA: So you've somehow slashed the cost of building a rocket by 75 percent, depending on how you calculate it. How on Earth have you done that? NASA has been doing this for years. How have you done this? EM: Well, we've made significant advances in the technology of the airframe, the engines, the electronics and the launch operation. There's a long list of innovations that we've come up with there that are a little difficult to communicate in this talk, but -- CA: Not least because you could still get copied, right? You haven't patented this stuff. It's really interesting to me. EM: No, we don't patent.CA: You didn't patent because you think it's more dangerous to patent than not to patent. EM: Since our primary competitors are national governments, the enforceability of patents is questionable.(Laughter) (Applause) CA: That's really, really interesting. But the big innovation is still ahead, and you're working on it now. Tell us about this. EM: Right, so the big innovation— CA: In fact, let's roll that video and you can talk us through it, what's happening here. EM: Absolutely. So the thing about rockets is that they're all expendable. All rockets that fly today are fully expendable. The space shuttle was an attempt at a reusable rocket, but even the main tank of the space shuttle was thrown away every time, and the parts that were reusable took a 10,000-person group nine months to refurbish for flight. So the space shuttle ended up costing a billion dollars per flight. Obviously that doesn't work very well for — CA: What just happened there? We just saw something land? EM: That's right. So it's important that the rocket stages be able to come back, to be able to return to the launch site and be ready to launch again within a matter of hours. CA: Wow. Reusable rockets.EM: Yes. (Applause) And so what a lot of people don't realize is, the cost of the fuel, of the propellant, is very small. It's much like on a jet. So the cost of the propellant is about .3 percent of the cost of the rocket. So it's possible to achieve, let's say, roughly 100-fold improvement in the cost of spaceflight if you can effectively reuse the rocket. That's why it's so important. Every mode of transport that we use, whether it's planes, trains, automobiles, bikes, horses, is reusable, but not rockets. So we must solve this problem in order to become a space-faring civilization. CA: You asked me the question earlier of how popular traveling on cruises would be if you had to burn your ships afterward.EM: Certain cruises are apparently highly problematic. CA: Definitely more expensive. So that's potentially absolutely disruptive technology, and, I guess, paves the way for your dream to actually take, at some point, to take humanity to Mars at scale. You'd like to see a colony on Mars. EM: Yeah, exactly. SpaceX, or some combination of companies and governments, needs to make progress in the direction of making life multi-planetary, of establishing a base on another planet, on Mars -- being the only realistic option -- and then building that base up until we're a true multi-planet species. CA: So progress on this "let's make it reusable," how is that going? That was just a simulation video we saw. How's it going? EM: We're actually, we've been making some good progress recently with something we call the Grasshopper Test Project, where we're testing the vertical landing portion of the flight, the sort of terminal portion which is quite tricky. And we've had some good tests. CA: Can we see that?EM: Yeah. So that's just to give a sense of scale. We dressed a cowboy as Johnny Cash and bolted the mannequin to the rocket. (Laughter) CA: All right, let's see that video then, because this is actually amazing when you think about it. You've never seen this before. A rocket blasting off and then -- EM: Yeah, so that rocket is about the size of a 12-story building. (Rocket launch) So now it's hovering at about 40 meters, and it's constantly adjusting the angle, the pitch and yaw of the main engine, and maintaining roll with cold gas thrusters. CA: How cool is that? (Applause) Elon, how have you done this? These projects are so -- Paypal, SolarCity, Tesla, SpaceX, they're so spectacularly different, they're such ambitious projects at scale. How on Earth has one person been able to innovate in this way? What is it about you? EM: I don't know, actually. I don't have a good answer for you. I work a lot. I mean, a lot. CA: Well, I have a theory.EM: Okay. All right. CA: My theory is that you have an ability to think at a system level of design that pulls together design, technology and business, so if TED was TBD, design, technology and business, into one package, synthesize it in a way that very few people can and -- and this is the critical thing -- feel so damn confident in that clicked-together package that you take crazy risks. You bet your fortune on it, and you seem to have done that multiple times. I mean, almost no one can do that. Is that -- could we have some of that secret sauce? Can we put it into our education system? Can someone learn from you? It is truly amazing what you've done. EM: Well, thanks. Thank you. Well, I do think there's a good framework for thinking. It is physics. You know, the sort of first principles reasoning. Generally I think there are -- what I mean by that is, boil things down to their fundamental truths and reason up from there, as opposed to reasoning by analogy. Through most of our life, we get through life by reasoning by analogy, which essentially means copying what other people do with slight variations. And you have to do that. Otherwise, mentally, you wouldn't be able to get through the day. But when you want to do something new, you have to apply the physics approach. Physics is really figuring out how to discover new things that are counterintuitive, like quantum mechanics. It's really counterintuitive. So I think that's an important thing to do, and then also to really pay attention to negative feedback, and solicit it, particularly from friends. This may sound like simple advice, but hardly anyone does that, and it's incredibly helpful. CA: Boys and girls watching, study physics. Learn from this man. Elon Musk, I wish we had all day, but thank you so much for coming to TED. EM: Thank you. CA: That was awesome. That was really, really cool. Look at that. (Applause) Just take a bow. That was fantastic. Thank you so much.
Dispone de unos 400 kilómetros de autonomía. CA: El paquete de baterías es muy pesado. ¿Crees que todavía pueden salir las cuentas si combinamos una carrocería ligera con unas baterías pesadas? ¿Todavía se puede obtener una eficiencia espectacular? EM: Exacto. El resto del coche tiene que ser muy ligero para compensar la masa del paquete de baterías. También hay que conseguir un coeficiente aerodinámico bajo para tener buena autonomía en la carretera. De hecho, muchos usuarios del Tesla Modelo S están como compitiendo entre ellos para alcanzar la mayor autonomía posible. Creo que alguien obtuvo hace poco unos 670 kilómetros con una sola carga. CA: Bruno Bowden, que está aquí, lo hizo. Batió el récord mundial. EM: ¡Felicidades! CA: Esa es la buena noticia. La mala noticia es que, para hacerlo, tuvo que andar a 30 kilómetros por hora hasta que lo paró la policía. (Risas) EM: Claro, realmente puedes conducir... si vas a 100 kilómetros por hora, en circunstancias normales, 400 kilómetros es una cifra razonable. CA: Vamos a ver el segundo video que nos muestra al Tesla en acción sobre hielo. Por cierto, no es para nada, una indirecta al New York Times. ¿Qué es lo más sorprendente al conducir el coche? EM: Al crear un coche eléctrico, la respuesta del coche es simplemente increíble. Queríamos que la gente se sintiera como si casi se hubieran fundido con el coche, como si persona y coche fueran uno, y si tomas una curva y aceleras, es instantáneo, el coche tiene ESP. Con un coche eléctrico esto es posible debido a su gran respuesta. No es posible con un coche de gasolina. Creo que esa es la gran diferencia, y la gente solo puede experimentarla al probar el coche. CA: En realidad se trata de un coche precioso y muy caro. ¿Tienes un plan para que este vehículo llegue a ser un producto de masas? EM: Así es. La meta de Tesla siempre ha sido tener una especie de proceso de tres pasos, el primer producto sería un coche caro de bajo volumen de ventas, el segundo producto es un coche con precio y volumen promedio y el tercero sería un coche de precio bajo y gran volumen de ventas. Estamos en el paso dos en este momento. Es decir, tenemos un deportivo de 100.000 dólares, el Tesla Roadster. Después está el Tesla Modelo S, que parte de unos $50.000. Y por último nuestro coche de tercera generación que debe salir en unos 3 ó 4 años con un precio de unos $30.000. En realidad siempre que creas tecnología nueva, se necesitan unas tres versiones para lograr un producto atractivo para consumo masivo. Yo creo que estamos progresando en esa dirección y tengo confianza en que alcanzaremos la meta. CA: Es decir, ahora mismo, si la distancia al trabajo es corta, puedes ir y volver en el coche y recargarlo en casa. Actualmente no existe una gran red nacional de estaciones de recarga que sean rápidas. ¿Crees de verdad que eso llegará o en realidad solo habrá en unas pocas rutas importantes? EM: En realidad hay más estaciones de recarga de lo que la gente cree. En Tesla estamos desarrollando lo que llamamos tecnología de supercargadores y se la estamos ofreciendo a los compradores del Modelo S de manera gratuita y para siempre. Esto es algo que, tal vez, mucha gente desconoce. En la actualidad tenemos cubiertas California y Nevada, así como la costa este de los EEUU, desde Boston a Washington D.C. Para final de año, se podrá conducir desde Los Angeles a Nueva York usando la red de supercargadores, que recarga cinco veces más rápido que las demás alternativas. La clave está en tener una proporción de conducción-parada de uno a seis o siete. Es decir, si conduces durante tres horas, haces una parada de unos 20 ó 30 minutos, porque es lo que la gente haría normalmente. Si el viaje empieza a las 9 a.m., al mediodía lo normal es hacer una parada para comer algo ir al baño, tomar un café y seguir la marcha. CA: Tu propuesta es entonces una hora para una recarga completa. Es normal... no se puede esperar estar en marcha tras 10 minutos. Hay que esperar una hora, pero lo bueno es que estás ayudando a salvar el planeta y, además, la electricidad es gratis. No hay que pagar nada. EM: En realidad, lo que queremos es que la gente pare unos 20 o 30 minutos, no una hora. En realidad es mejor conducir unos 250 kilómetros, parar media hora y continuar el viaje. Es la cadencia natural de un viaje. CA: Perfecto. Y esto es solo una carta de tu baraja energética. Estás también trabajando en la compañía de energía solar SolarCity. ¿Qué tiene de especial? EM: Bien, como he mencionado antes, tenemos que tener una producción sostenible de energía, así como el consumo, pues estoy bien convencido de que los medios principales de generación de energía serán solares. Es decir, realmente se trata de fusión indirecta, sí. Tenemos ese reactor de fusión natural en el cielo que es el Sol. Solo tenemos que atrapar un poco de esa energía para servirnos de ella. Hay algo que mucha gente sabe aun sin pensarlo y es que el mundo ya funciona casi completamente con energía solar. Sin el Sol, el mundo sería una esfera helada a 3 grados Kelvin. Del Sol también dependen las lluvias. Todo el ecosistema depende del Sol. CA: Pero en un litro de gasolina tenemos, de hecho, miles de años de energía solar concentrados en algo bien compacto, por lo que es difícil que salgan las cuentas ahora con energía solar. Para poder competir, por ejemplo, con gas natural, ¿Cómo planteas tu negocio respecto a esto? EM: En realidad estoy convencido de que la energía solar superará a todo y, sin duda, también al gas natural. (Aplausos) CA: ¿Y cómo? EM: Bueno, tiene que ser así. Si no, tendremos serios problemas. CA: Pero no estás vendiendo páneles solares a los clientes. ¿Qué estás haciendo? EM: En realidad sí se los vendemos. El cliente puede comprar o tomar en leasing la instalación solar. La mayoría elige el leasing. Lo bueno de la energía solar es que no requiere materias primas ni tiene costos operativos solo hay que instalarla, eso es todo. Funciona durante décadas. Probablemente incluso un siglo. Por lo que la clave es conseguir que el costo de la instalación incial sea bajo y que la financiación sea baja, porque ese interés... esos son los dos factores que componen el costo de la energía solar. Hemos hecho grandes progresos en esa dirección, por eso estoy convencido de que superaremos al gas natural. CA: Lo que propones a los clientes es que no paguen mucho inicialmente. EM: Cero. CA: Que no paguen nada inicialmente. Nosotros instalamos los paneles en el techo. Y ellos pagan después. ¿Cuánto dura un leasing? EM: Lo típico es 20 años. Lo que proponemos, como sugieres, es muy sencillo. No hay que poner dinero y la cuenta de electricidad baja. Un buen trato. CA: Todo parece bonito para el consumidor. Sin riesgos y se paga menos que ahora. Lo ideal sería... Quiero decir, ¿A quién le pertenece la electricidad de los paneles a largo plazo? ¿Dónde está el beneficio para tu compañia? EM: Bueno, básicamente, SolarCity consigue capital de, digamos, una compañia o un banco. Google es uno de nuestros grandes socios aquí. Esas compañías tienen una esperanza de retorno del capital. Con ese capital, SolarCity compra e instala los panales en el techo y cobra al propietario de la vivienda o del negocio una cuota mensual de leasing que es menos que su factura eléctrica. CA: Pero tu obtienes un beneficio comercial a largo plazo de esa energía. Estás creando un nuevo tipo de suministro de servicio eléctrico. EM: Exacto. Se trata de un gran sistema de suministro. Creo que es positivo, porque el servicio eléctrico siempre ha sido un monopolio y la gente no ha podido elegir. Efectivamente, por primera vez habrá competencia ante ese monopolio. Las empresas de energía siempre han sido propietarias de las redes de distribución. Pero ahora todo estará en el techo. Creo que es ventajoso para los propietarios de viviendas y para los negocios. CA: ¿De verdad te imaginas un futuro en el que la mayoría de la energía de los EEUU en una década o dos, o durante tu vida, sea solar? EM: Estoy convencido de que la energía solar será parte del abanico energético, y, probablemente, la preferida. Además pronostico que esto sucederá en menos de 20 años. Lo he apostado con alguien. CA: ¿Cómo defines ese abanico energético? EM: Más energía solar que de otras fuentes. CA: ¡Ah! ¿con quién lo has apostado? EM: Con un amigo que permanecerá en el anonimato. CA: Aquí entre nosotros. (Risa) EM: La apuesta la hicimos hará unos dos o tres años, por lo que, en unos 18 años, creo que la energía solar será la fuente principal de energía. CA: Muy bien, volvamos a otra apuesta que hiciste contigo mismo. Una apuesta bastante disparatada. Conseguiste algo de dinero con la venta de PayPal y decidiste montar una empresa aeroespacial. ¿Por qué demonios hiciste algo así? (Risas) EM: Me hacen mucho esa pregunta, es verdad. La gente diría: "¿Te sabes el chiste sobre el tío que hizo una pequeña fortuna en la industria aeroespacial?" Obviamente, el final es: "Bueno, empezó con una grande". Lo que le digo a la gente es que estaba buscando la forma más rápida de convertir una gran fortuna en una pequeña. Y siempre me miran como diciendo: "¿lo dices en serio?" CA: Extrañamente ibas en serio. ¿Qué pasó? EM: Muy cerca. Las cosas casi que no funcionaban. Estuvimos muy cerca de fracasar, pero conseguimos superar ese punto en 2008. El objetivo de SpaceX es impulsar la tecnología aeroespacial y, en concreto, tratar de resolver un problema que, creo, es vital para la humanidad para poder volverse una civilización espacial Se trata de contar con un cohete totalmente reutilizable. CA: ¿Conquistará la humanidad el espacio en algún momento? ¿Es ese tu sueño desde pequeño? ¿Soñabas con Marte y más allá? EM: Cuando era un niño ya construía cohetes, pero nunca pensé que llegaría a involucrarme en ello. En realidad era más con el enfoque de, en qué cosas necesita el futuro para llegar a ser apasionante y estimulante. Realmente creo que hay una diferencia fundamental, si miras al futuro, entre una humanidad que conquista el espacio, que explora las estrellas, que está en muchos planetas, creo que es apasionante, comparado con una en la que estamos confinados en la Tierra para siempre hasta una posible extinción final. CA: Has reducido el costo de construcción de un cohete en un 75%, según cómo se calcule. ¿Cómo demonios lo has conseguido? La NASA lleva años en esto. ¿Cómo lo has logrado? EM: Bueno, hemos progresado mucho en tecnología de estructuras, de motores, de componentes electrónicos y en el lanzamiento. Hay una lista larga de innovaciones que hemos logrado que serían difíciles de explicar en esta charla, pero... CA: Además podrían copiarte, ¿no? No has patentado nada de esto. Me parece muy interesante. EM: No, no patentamos nada. CA: No patentas porque creés que es más peligroso patentar que no patentar. EM: Ya que nuestros principales competidores son los gobiernos, la efectividad de las patentes es cuestionable.(Risas) (Aplausos) CA: Es muy interesante. Pero la gran innovación está por venir y ya estás trabajando en ello. Cuéntanos un poco. EM: Bien, la gran innovación... CA: De hecho, podemos poner el video y nos vas comentando de qué se trata. EM: Por supuesto. La cuestión con los cohetes es que se pierden al desprenderse. Todos los cohetes que se lanzan hoy en día son así. El transbordador espacial es un intento de cohete reutilizable, pero incluso el tanque principal del trasbordador se desechaba y las partes reutilizables necesitaban un grupo de 10.000 personas y nueve meses para poder ser reutilizadas en otro vuelo. Por eso el trasbordador espacial terminó costando mil millones de dólares por vuelo. Obviamente no es lo mejor... CA: ¿Qué pasó ahí? ¿Vimos algo aterrizando? EM: Así es. Lo importante es que las etapas del cohete puedan volver, puedan regresar al lugar de lanzamiento y estén listas para el próximo lanzamiento en cuestión de horas. CA: Increíble, cohetes reutilizables. EM: Sí. (Aplausos) Mucha gente no se da cuenta de que el costo del combustible, del propulsor, es muy pequeño. Es casi como en un jet. El costo del propulsor es de cerca del 0,3 por ciento del costo del cohete. Por lo que es posible, digamos, una reducción de casi 100 veces en los costos del vuelo espacial si se logra reutilizar el cohete. Por eso es tan imporante. Todos los medios de transporte que usamos, ya sean aviones, trenes, automóviles, bicicletas o caballos son reutilizables excepto los cohetes. Por lo que tenemos que resolver este problema si queremos llegar a conquistar el espacio. CA: Me preguntabas antes que qué popularidad tendrían los cruceros si después tuviéramos que quemar las naves. EM: Sí, algunos cruceros parecen ser muy problemáticos. CA: Sin duda mucho más caros. Estamos ante una tecnología deshechadora en potencia. Supongo que esto allana el camino hacia tu sueño de llevar parte de la humanidad a Marte. Te encantaría ver una colonia en Marte. EM: Sí, exacto. SpaceX, o una combinación de compañias y gobiernos tienen que progresar en hacer de la vida algo multiplanetario. En establecer bases en otros planetas, en Marte --que es la única opción realista-- y luego ampliar esa base hasta que seamos una especie multiplanetaria. CA: ¿Y el avance en este "vamos a reutilizar"? ¿Cómo se está dando? El video que hemos visto era solo una simulación. ¿Cómo van las cosas? EM: En realidad hemos avanzado mucho últimamente con algo que llamamos el Proyecto de Prueba Saltamontes, con el que estamos probando la parte del aterrizaje vertical del vuelo, que es la parte final y es bastante complicada. Hemos tenido buenos resultados en las pruebas. CA: ¿Podemos verlo? EM: Claro. Esto es solo para dar una idea de la escala. Disfrazamos a un cowboy de Johnny Cash y despues atornillamos el maniquí al cohete. (Risas) CA: Muy bien, veamos el video entonces, porque, si te lo planteas, es realmente increíble. Es algo nunca visto antes. Un cohete despegando y entonces... EM: Sí, el cohete tiene la altura de un edificio de 12 plantas. (Lanzamiento del cohete) Ahora mismo está flotando a unos 40 metros y está ajustando constantemente el ángulo, el cabeceo, el viraje del motor principal y equilibrándose con propulsores a gas de carbón. CA: Es genial. (Aplausos) Elon, ¿cómo lo has conseguido? Estos proyectos son tan... Paypal, SolarCity, Tesla, SpaceX, son tremendamente diferentes. Son proyectos muy ambiciosos a gran escala. ¿Cómo demonios una sola persona puede innovar de esta manera? ¿Cuál es tu secreto? EM: En realidad no lo sé. Creo que no tengo respuesta para eso. Trabajo mucho, muchísimo. CA: Bueno, yo tengo una teoría. EM: Bien, veamos. CA: Mi teoría es que eres capaz de pensar a nivel del sistema que conjuga tecnología, negocios y diseño, de tal manera que si TED fuese TND, tecnología, negocios y diseño, todo en un paquete, y lo sintetizas de una manera que muy pocos pueden, y esto es lo más crítico, y además te sientes tan seguro cuando todo encaja, que eres capaz de asumir riesgos enormes. Arriesgas tu fortuna en ello, y parece que lo has hecho varias veces. Prácticamente nadie puede hacer algo así. Es... ¿podemos beber un poco de esa poción mágica? ¿Podemos poner un poco en nuestro sistema educativo? ¿Podemos aprender de ti? Es realmente increíble lo que has conseguido. EM: Bueno, gracias. Muchas gracias. Creo que hay un ámbito perfecto para pensar. La física. Es decir, los principios básicos. Por regla general pienso que hay que... lo que quiero decir es, que hay que reducir las cosas a sus bases fundamentales y empezar a razonar desde ahí, por oposición a trabajar por analogía. Vamos por la vida, en su mayor parte, razonando por analogía, que, básicamente, implica copiar lo que hacen los demás con pequeñas variaciones. Y hay que hacerlo así. Si no, mentalmente no podríamos soportar ni un día. Pero cuando quieres hacer algo nuevo tienes que aplicar la estrategia de la física. La física consiste en ingeniárselas para descubrir cosas nuevas, contrarias a la intuición, como la mecánica cuántica. Va muy en contra de la intuición. Creo que es importante hacerlo así. Y también prestar atención a las críticas adversas e incluso pedirlas, especialmente a los amigos. Esto puede parecer un simple consejo, pero casi nadie lo hace. y es tremendamente útil. CA: Chicos y chicas que nos están viendo, estudien física. Aprendan de este hombre. Elon Musk, ojala tuviésemos todo el día... Pero muchas gracias por venir a TED. EM: Gracias a ti. CA: Ha sido maravilloso, verdaderamente genial. Mírenlo. (Aplausos) Saluda al público. Ha sido fantástico. Muchísimas gracias.